Guide to the Tiffany and Company Stationery Collection 1875-1960 PR 433
New-York Historical Society
Tiffany and Company stationery collection
1875-1960
New-York Historical Society
Tiffany and Company
PR 433
16.3 Linear feet in 17 boxes
Printed samples from the stationery department of Tiffany and Company. Samples date from 1875 to 1960, and include invitations, letterhead, envelopes, at-home cards, visiting and calling cards, admission tickets, certificates, dinner party menus, and holiday cards.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by format.
Biographical / Historical
In 1837, Charles Lewis Tiffany and John B. Young opened a "stationery and fancy goods emporium" at 259 Broadway in New York City. Charles Tiffany's father Comfort Tiffany financed the store with a $1,000 loan. Initially known as Tiffany & Young (1837-1841) and later Tiffany, Young & Ellis (1841-1853),the store sold stationery products, glassware, silverware, jewelry, and porcelain. Unlike other stores at the time, Tiffany clearly marked the prices on its goods (to avoid haggling); only accepted cash payments; and did not allow purchases on credit. The first Tiffany mail order catalog, known as the "Blue Book", was published in 1845.
Charles Lewis Tiffany took sole control of the company in 1853, renamed it Tiffany & Company, and established the company's emphasis on jewelry, especially pieces featuring silver and precious stones. By 1877, the company had acquired the Tiffany diamond, a large yellow stone from the Kimberley Mines in South Africa. In 1887, Tiffany acquired major pieces at the sale of the French Crown Jewels in Paris.
On his father's death in 1902, Louis Comfort Tiffany became design director, and the company became one of the leading proponents of the Art Nouveau style. In 1905, the Manhattan flagship store was relocated to the corner of 37th Street and Fifth Avenue; it moved to the present address, Fifth Avenue and 57th street, in 1940.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
For offsite material: Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact printroom@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
No accession information is available.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed samples from the stationery department of Tiffany and Company. Samples date from 1875 to 1960, and include invitations, letterhead, envelopes, at-home cards, admission tickets, certificates, dinner party menus, and holiday cards (mainly Christmas cards). Also included are examples of identifying cards: Small cards bearing the name, and sometimes the address, of a person for presentation, i.e. business, calling and visiting cards. as when formally calling or visiting cards. There are 7 bound sample books, 2 of which were created to showcase the work of the stationery department at the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo, New York. The remainder of the collection is loose ephemera. Most individual items have a Tiffany watermark or printed mark. Some are embossed with "Sample to be returned to Tiffany & Co." Of special interest are invitations to wedding anniversary celebrations printed on linen, wood, and tin to correspond with the traditional gifts given on the respective anniversaries: 4th-linen; 5th-wood; and 10th-tin.
Business cards.; Certificates.; Invitations.; Menus.; Sample books; Stationery; Visiting cards
- Cards, Holiday, 1900-1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-5)
- Cards, Identifying, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-5)
  Scope and Contents
  small cards bearing the name, and sometimes the address, of a person for presentation, i.e. business cards, calling cards and visiting cards
- Cards, Other, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-8)
  admission cards, escort cards, reminder cards
- Cards, Other, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-5)
  tally cards, thank you cards, transportation cards, miscellaneous
- Certificates, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  includes awards, diplomas, membership certificates
- Certificates, Oversize, undated (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1)
- Invitations, 1875-1960 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-5)
  from arts and science organizations, business organizations, and social clubs
- Invitations, 1875-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-7)
  from social clubs, fraternal organizations, fundraisers, government and international organizations, and lineage societies
- Invitations, 1875-1960 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-6)
  for military events, private events, and public ceremonies including the Hudson-Fulton Celebration, Washington's Inaugural Centennial, the opening of the Statue of Liberty, and the opening of the Empire State Building
- Invitations, 1875-1960 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-6)
  for events at schools and colleges, weddings, and wedding anniversary celebrations
- Invitations, Oversize, 1893-1926 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 2)
- Letterhead, General, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-10)
- Letterhead, General, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-2)
- Letterhead, Yachts, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-5)
  stationery personalized with the name of a yacht
- Menus, 1900-1960 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 3-6)
  for dinner parties and events
- Menus, Oversize (1 menu), 1919 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 3)
- Sample Books, Christmas Cards (2 volumes), 1909-1936 (Offsite-box 12)
- Sample Books, Engraving Proofs, 1889-1904 (Offsite-box 13)
- Sample Books, General, 1889 (Offsite-box 14)
- Sample Books, Pan-American Exposition, Volume 1, 1901 (Offsite-box 15)
  created to showcase samples of the work of the stationery department to consumers at the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo, New York
- Sample Books, Pan-American Exposition, Volume 2, 1901 (Offsite-box 16)
  created to showcase samples of the work of the stationery department to consumers at the 1901 Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo, New York.
- Sample Books, Wedding Invitations, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 17)